[
  {
    "id": "FA2-NCA-S4-1",
    "questionType": "numerical",
    "questionText": "On 1 January RiverBay purchased an item of plant. The invoice showed: <br>$<br>Cost of plant 48,000<br>Delivery to factory 400<br>One year warranty covering breakdown 800<br>49,200<br>In addition, modifications to the factory building costing $2,200 were necessary to enable the plant to be installed.<br>What amount should be capitalised for the plant in the accounting records of the business?<br>$",
    "correctAnswer": 50600,
    "entryInstructions": "",
    "explanation": "Cost of plant $48,000<br>Delivery $400<br>Modifications $2,200<br>-----<br>$50,600"
  },
  {
    "id": "FA2-NCA-S4-2",
    "questionType": "mcq",
    "questionText": "A non-current asset was purchased at the beginning of Year 1 for $2,400 and depreciated by 20% per annum using the reducing balance method. At the beginning of Year 4 it was sold for $1,200.<br>What was the profit or loss on disposal?",
    "options": [
      "A loss on disposal of $240.00",
      "A loss on disposal of $28.80",
      "A profit on disposal of $28.80",
      "A profit on disposal of $240.00"
    ],
    "correctOptions": [
      1
    ],
    "explanation": "Year 1<br>Cost $2,400.0<br>Depreciation at 20% (480.0)<br>Carrying value $1,920.0<br><br>Year 2<br>Depreciation at 20% (384.0)<br>Carrying value $1,536.0<br><br>Year 3<br>Depreciation at 20% (307.2)<br>Carrying value $1,228.8<br><br>Year 4<br>Sale proceeds $1,200.0<br>Loss on disposal (28.8)"
  },
  {
    "id": "FA2-NCA-S4-3",
    "questionType": "numerical",
    "questionText": "SkyVision's non-current assets had a carrying amount of $125,000.<br>An asset which had cost $12,000 was sold for $9,000, at a profit of $2,000.<br>What was the revised carrying amount of non-current assets?<br>$",
    "correctAnswer": 118000,
    "entryInstructions": "",
    "explanation": "Original balance $125,000<br>Carrying amount of asset sold:<br>Proceeds $9,000<br>Less: Profit ($2,000)<br>($7,000)<br>Adjusted balance $118,000"
  },
  {
    "id": "FA2-NCA-S4-4",
    "questionType": "numerical",
    "questionText": "A non-current asset was disposed of for $2,200 during the last accounting year. It had been purchased exactly three years earlier for $5,000, with an expected residual value of $500, and had been depreciated on the reducing balance basis, at 20% per annum.<br>What was the loss on disposal?<br>$",
    "correctAnswer": 360,
    "entryInstructions": "",
    "explanation": "Cost $5,000<br>Year 1 (20% x 5,000) ($1,000)<br>Year 2 (20% x 4,000) ($800)<br>Year 3 (20% × 3,200) ($640)<br>Carrying amount at time of disposal $2,560<br>Sale proceeds $2,200<br>Loss on disposal $360"
  },
  {
    "id": "FA2-NCA-S4-5",
    "questionType": "mcq",
    "questionText": "Which TWO of the following items should be accounted for as asset expenditure?",
    "options": [
      "The purchase of a car for a member of the sales department to visit clients",
      "The purchase of a car for resale by a car dealer",
      "Legal fees incurred on the purchase of a building",
      "The cost of painting a building"
    ],
    "correctOptions": [
      0,
      2
    ],
    "explanation": "The purchase of a car for resale means that the car is an item of inventory for the business, not a non-current asset. Legal fees incurred in purchasing a building are included in the cost of the building, and so is part of the non-current asset cost, i.e. asset expenditure. The cost of maintenance (i.e. painting a building) is an expense. The cost of purchasing a car for use by an employee performing their work duties should be capitalised."
  },
  {
    "id": "FA2-NCA-S4-6",
    "questionType": "numerical",
    "questionText": "A car was purchased for $12,000 on 1 April and has been depreciated at 20% each year straight line, assuming no residual value. The accounting policy of the business is to charge a full year's depreciation in the year of purchase and no depreciation in the year of sale. The car was traded in for a replacement vehicle on 1 August for an agreed figure of $5,000.<br>What was the profit on the disposal of the vehicle for the year ended 31 December<br>$",
    "correctAnswer": 200,
    "entryInstructions": "",
    "explanation": "NCA Disposal<br>Cost $12,000<br>Accumulated depreciation (3 yrs x 20% x $12,000) $7,200<br>Profit (β) $200<br>Proceeds (part-exchange allowance) $5,000<br>Totals $12,200<br>Totals $12,200"
  },
  {
    "id": "FA2-NCA-S4-7",
    "questionType": "mcq",
    "questionText": "A business accounted for the repair of an item of plant and machinery as asset expenditure in the accounting records.<br>What is the effect of this error upon the profit for the year and also upon the carrying amount of assets included in the statement of financial position before the error is corrected?",
    "options": [
      "Profit for the year is understated and assets on the statement of financial position are overstated.",
      "Profit for the year is overstated and assets on the statement of financial position are overstated.",
      "Profit for the year is understated and assets on the statement of financial position are understated.",
      "Profit for the year is overstated and assets on the statement of financial position are understated."
    ],
    "correctOptions": [
      1
    ],
    "explanation": "If an amount has been wrongly capitalised, rather than treated as an expense, the profit for the year will be higher than it should be. In addition, assets are overstated as they include an amount that should not have been capitalised."
  },
  {
    "id": "FA2-NCA-S4-8",
    "questionType": "mcq",
    "questionText": "A business accounted for the purchase of a new delivery truck as a motor expense in the accounting records.<br>What is the effect of this error upon the profit for the year and also upon the carrying amount of assets included in the statement of financial position before the error is corrected?",
    "options": [
      "Profit for the year is understated and assets on the statement of financial position are overstated.",
      "Profit for the year is overstated and assets on the statement of financial position are overstated.",
      "Profit for the year is understated and assets on the statement of financial position are understated.",
      "Profit for the year is overstated and assets on the statement of financial position are understated."
    ],
    "correctOptions": [
      2
    ],
    "explanation": "If an amount has been wrongly accounted for as an expense, rather than capitalised, the profit for the year will be lower than it should be. In addition, assets are understated as they exclude an amount that should have been capitalised and accounted for as a non-current asset."
  },
  {
    "id": "FA2-NCA-S4-9",
    "questionType": "numerical",
    "questionText": "PaperFox purchased an item of plant at a cost of $100,000 in 1 January It was expected to last for ten years and have a scrap value of $10,000. PaperFox depreciates non-current assets at 20% on the reducing balance basis. The item of plant was sold on 1 April 20X4 for sale proceeds of $70,000. It is PaperFox's policy to charge a full year of depreciation in the year of purchase and none in the year of disposal. PaperFox has an accounting year end of 31 December.<br>What was the profit on disposal on this asset?<br>$",
    "correctAnswer": 6000,
    "entryInstructions": "",
    "explanation": "NCA Disposal<br>Cost $100,000<br>20X2 dep'n (100,000 × 20%) $20,000<br>20X3 dep'n (800,000 × 20%) $16,000<br>Profit (β) $6,000<br>Disposal proceeds $70,000<br>Totals $106,000<br>Totals $106,000"
  },
  {
    "id": "FA2-NCA-S4-10",
    "questionType": "numerical",
    "questionText": "Owen purchased an item of plant at a cost of $100,000 in 1 January 20X2. It was expected to last for six years and had an estimated scrap value of $10,000 at the end of that time.<br>Owen depreciates non-current assets on a straight-line basis, with a proportionate charge in the year of purchase and disposal. Owen has an accounting year end of 31 December.<br>The item of plant subsequently was sold on 1 April 20X4 for sale proceeds of $60,000.<br>What was the loss on disposal on this asset?<br>$",
    "correctAnswer": 6250,
    "entryInstructions": "",
    "explanation": "NCA Disposal<br>Cost $100,000<br>20X2 dep'n ((100,000 - 10,000)/6) $15,000<br>20X3 dep'n ((100,000 - 10,000)/6) $15,000<br>20X4 dep'n ((100,000 - 10,000)/6 × 3/12) $3,750<br>Disposal proceeds $60,000<br>Loss on disposal (β) $6,250<br>Totals $100,000<br>Totals $100,000"
  },
  {
    "id": "FA2-NCA-S4-12",
    "questionType": "numerical",
    "questionText": "A machine which had cost of $20,000 and had accumulated depreciation of $17,200 was sold during for $4,800. The totalcost of machinery shown in the December 20X6 statement of financial position was $180,000 and the related accumulated depreciation was $92,000. The business uses 10% straight-line depreciation on machinery and no depreciation is charged in the year in which an asset is sold.<br>What was the balance on the accumulated depreciation account at 31 December 20X7?",
    "correctAnswer": 90800,
    "entryInstructions": "",
    "explanation": "Depreciation<br>Debit:<br>Disposal $17,200<br>31/12/X7 Bal c/d $90,800<br>Totals $108,000<br>Credit:<br>1/1/X7 Bal b/d $92,000<br>31/12/X7 Profit or loss statement $16,000<br>Totals $108,000<br>1/1/X8 Bal b/d $90,800"
  },
  {
    "id": "FA2-NCA-S4-13",
    "questionType": "numerical",
    "questionText": "A machine which had cost of $20,000 and had accumulated depreciation of $17,200 was sold during for $4,800. The totalcost of machinery shown in the December 20X6 statement of financial position was $180,000 and the related accumulated depreciation was $92,000. The business uses 10% straight-line depreciation on machinery and no depreciation is charged in the year in which an asset is sold.<br>What was the profit on disposal of the machine?",
    "correctAnswer": 2000,
    "entryInstructions": "",
    "explanation": "Disposal<br>Debit:<br>Cost $20,000<br>31/12/X7 Profit or loss $2,000<br>Totals $22,000<br>Credit:<br>Dep'n $17,200<br>Bank $4,800<br>Totals $22,000"
  },
  {
    "id": "FA2-NCA-S4-14",
    "questionType": "numerical",
    "questionText": "A machine which had cost of $20,000 and had accumulated depreciation of $17,200 was sold during for $4,800. The totalcost of machinery shown in the December 20X6 statement of financial position was $180,000 and the related accumulated depreciation was $92,000. The business uses 10% straight-line depreciation on machinery and no depreciation is charged in the year in which an asset is sold.<br>What was the annual depreciation charge for 20X7?",
    "correctAnswer": 16000,
    "entryInstructions": "",
    "explanation": "Cost<br>1/1/X7 Bal b/d $180,000<br>Totals $180,000<br>31/12/X7 Disposal $20,000<br>Bal c/d $160,000<br>Totals $180,000<br>NCA Cost $160,000 x 10% = $16,000 = depreciation charge"
  },
  {
    "id": "FA2-NCA-S4-15",
    "questionType": "mcq",
    "questionText": "What entries are required in the disposal of asset account in the general ledger to record the sale of the machine in 20X7?",
    "options": [
      "Debit Accumulated depreciation $9,600<br>Credit Bank $4,800",
      "Debit Machinery $3,400<br>Credit Machinery $4,800",
      "Debit Accumulated depreciation $1,400<br>Credit Bank $4,800",
      "Debit Machinery $22,000<br>Credit Bank $4,800",
      "Debit Machinery $20,000<br>Credit Accumulated depreciation $17,200",
      "Debit Profit on disposal $2,000<br>Credit Accumulated depreciation $17,200"
    ],
    "correctOptions": [
      3
    ],
    "explanation": "Disposal<br>Debit:<br>Cost $20,000<br>Profit or loss $2,000<br>Totals $22,000<br>Credit:<br>Dep'n $17,200<br>Bank $4,800<br>Totals $22,000"
  },
  {
    "id": "FA2-NCA-S4-16",
    "questionType": "mcq",
    "questionText": "Which of the following best describes the gain or loss on the disposal of a non-current?",
    "options": [
      "The amount by which management over or under charged depreciation for the asset.",
      "The extent to which the asset's underlying value changed during its useful life.",
      "The correction of forecasting errors when the asset's useful life and residual values were estimated.",
      "The remaining value after depreciation has been taken into account."
    ],
    "correctOptions": [
      2
    ],
    "explanation": "The gain or loss on disposal is the difference between the disposal value of the asset and its net book value at the date of disposal. If the asset's life and disposal value had been forecast with 100% accuracy, there would be no gain or loss on disposal."
  }
]